# 这是我兄弟找的司机来接我们
My buddy sent a driver to pick us up
# 现在我们从白云机场这边坐车到我兄弟家
Now we will take this car from Baiyun Airport to my buddy's place
# 大概4个小时左右
It will be about 4 hours
# 师傅你们知道华农兄弟它们拍视频吗
Hey bro, do you know about Huanong Brothers shooting videos?
# 知道啊
I do
Yeah
# 他们在我们那边都是名人哦很出名的
They are local celebrities. Very famous
# 名人 对
Yeah, celebrities
# 你们都属于网红
Both of you are Internet celebrities
# 哎呀 网不网红这个东西怎么说呢
Aiya, celebrity or not... It's like...
# 我觉得没有网不网红
I don't think that's a big deal
# 大家都是普通人嘛
We are all ordinary people
# 经过长途跋涉我们终于到了兄弟家
After a long journey, we've arrived at my buddy's place
# 总不能空手来
As we can't visit with our hands empty
# 我们带了
I've brought
# 我们自制的菜籽油 宽油
Our home made rapeseed oil. Or "kuan you" ("wide oil")
# 然后给我兄弟一人带了一盒月饼过来
And also one box of mooncake for each of my buddies
# 现在已经到了他们家门口了
Now we are in front of their gate
# 兄弟
Buddy!
# 兄弟来啦
You've arrived, buddy
# 买那么多东西干嘛提那么多东西
Why did you take so much stuff
# 来 里面请
Come in please
# 这个是自带的宽油
This is the "kuan you" that I brought by myself
# 里面坐里面坐
Take a seat inside
# 哇 你们的狗好有礼貌啊
Wow, your dogs are so polite
# 这狗不咬人的
These dogs don't bite
# 拎到这个就不烫
Hold this part (which is not hot)
# 这个玉米是兄弟家摘的
These corns are taken from my brother's place
# 兄弟家好多啊
He has so many
# 我们到外面吃吧
Let's eat outside
# 到外面吃吧
Eat outside
# 最近黑啦
You look tanned recently
# 是啊 经常晒太阳
Yeah, got a lot of sunlight recently
# 我给你介绍一下
Let me introduce them
# 这是我四伯
This is my uncle
# 专业的屠夫
A professional butcher
# 嘿嘿嘿
[laughters]
# 这个是
This is one of
# 我们班的同学
our students
# 你好你好
Hello, hello
# 你好
Hello
# 很漂亮哦
You're so pretty
# 你也很漂亮
You're so pretty, too
# 嘿嘿嘿
[laughters]
# 说明你漂亮好不好
That means you are really pretty
# 这个玉米很好吃的
This corn tastes really good
# 吃了玉米不会中暑吧
Will I get a heatstroke after eating this corn?
# 不会不会
No no no
# 这都是
These are all
# 兄弟家摘的
All taken from my brother's place
# 对了
By the way
# 我四伯说他想看一下你的竹鼠
Uncle said he wants to check out your bamboo rats
# 可以啊
Sure
# 介绍一下你的竹鼠
Introduce your bamboo rat
# 上次
And last time...
# 你们家那个
How is that one...
# 伊丽莎白鼠怎么样了
How's the "Elizabeth" rat?
# 好啊 还在上面那呢
Pretty good. Still up over there
# 越来越胖了
Fatter and fatter now
# 我们边走边聊
Let's go and chat
# 好 我们边走边聊
Yeah, let's go and chat
# 好
Yeah
# 就在上面
Right up over there
# 这鸡也不错
The chickens also look good
# 全都是母鸡
All are hens
# 咦 你们家猪呢
Eh, where are your pigs?
# 都被我关起来了
They're all locked up
# 关起来啦
Locked up?
# 不听话
Too naughty
# 到外面去拱
They go outside and eat...
# 拱别人家的白菜
Eat other people's cabbages
# 白菜
Cabbages?
# 它一出来的话就跑到外面去啦
If they are unlocked, they go outside immediately
# 习惯了
They're used to that
# 我们不在的时候经常跑到外面去
They always go outside when we're not here
# 到时候都
They may...
# 变野猪啦
They may become wild pigs if not locked
# 或者不见了
Or... just gone
# 那就亏大啦
That'll be a huge loss
# 嘿嘿嘿
[laughters]
# 好肥啊这竹鼠
The bamboo rats are so fat
# 一公二母
Each male with two females
# 好大
So huge
# 现在公鼠和母鼠的比例是1：7
Now the male-to-female ratio is, 1 to 7
# 那公鼠不是很累吗
Wouldn't the male rats be too exhausted?
# 没办法公的都卖光啦
I have no way. All the male rats are sold
# 就剩下一点点啦
Only a few are left
# 就只有轮着来嘛
So they have to rotate
# 这批怀孕就抓走再放别的进去
After one batch are pregnant, I'll take them away and put some others in
# 这公鼠太辛苦了
That's really hard work for the male rats
# 老是卖老是卖卖得公的都没多少个了
I've sold too much. There're not too many male rats left
# 母的又不舍得卖
And I don't want to sell the female ones
# 要下崽
They can give birth to new rats
# 这些都是
These are
# 一比二一比二这样子了
one-to-two or alike
# 听说你的伊丽莎白鼠很漂亮哦我看一下
I heard that your "Elizabeth" is very pretty. Can I take a look?
# 在那边
Over there
# 在哪里 我们看一下嘛
- Over there
- Let's take a look
# 哇 好漂亮啊
Wow, so pretty
# 真的很漂亮
So pretty, for real
# 好漂亮
So pretty
# 我怎么感觉它瘦了
I feel like... is he thinner than before?
# 这个不是伊丽莎白鼠
No, no. This isn't "Elizabeth"
# 哦
Oh
# 这个是没名字的
This doesn't have a name
# 无名莎白
"Namelessabeth"
# 嘿嘿嘿
[laughters]
# 但是它是白色的
It's also white
# 但是不听话
But really naughty
# 不听话还是很危险的
Naughty means dangerous
# 你看 跟兔子一样
Look, it's like a bunny
# 你看这个我抱它都不动
See, I can hold him like this and he doesn't move at all
# 很乖很乖
So gentle
# 公的还是母的
Male or female?
# 公的
Male
# 真的很乖
Really so gentle
# 不会咬人
He doesn't bite at all
# 那个就不行
The other one bites
# 这个很温顺
This is so gentle
# 很温顺的
So gentle
# 抱着它都没事
Can even hug him like this
# 来 跟大家打个招呼
Come on, say hi to the crowd
# 哈喽 一年不见甚是想念
Hello. It's been a year since we met last time. I missed you so much
# 它不会说话
He doesn't speak
# 它肯定想说大家好哦
He must want to say "hello everybody"
# 它这个白鼠跟黑鼠吃起来是不是不一样啊
Um... Do white rats taste differently from black rats?
# 这个我不知道
I have no idea
# 嘿嘿嘿
[laughters]
# 白的不好吃
White rats don't taste good
# 你居然不中套
Wow you dodged it
# 这个就是西西
This is Xi Xi
# 西西
Xi Xi
# 发给它做老婆啦
I assigned Xi Xi as his wife now
# 哦
Oh
# 后面生出来的就是白色的
So their babies will be white
# 这个是基因突变吗
Is it a genetic mutation?
# 对 他这个是基因突变
Yeah, a genetic mutation
# 全身都是白色的
The whole body is white
# 它要咬人的
They bite
# 你要小心哦它的牙齿特别厉害
You gotta watch it. Their teeth are very sharp
# 等下怕咬到你不要乱摸哦
Don't touch around. They may bite you
# 你要摸的话 提它的尾巴
If you want to touch it, raise it in the tail
# 这小的也会咬人的
Even this little one bites
# 小的也会咬人啊
Even little ones bite?
# 小的好可爱哦
The little one is so cute
# 你看它的牙齿还是白的还没变黄
Look, its teeth are still white. Haven't turned yellow yet
# 对 还没变黄
Right. Not yellow yet
# 慢慢的就变黄了
They'll turn yellow slowly
# 因为它还没断奶还在吃奶
It's still having milk. Not weaned yet
# 我提一下嘛
Can I hold it?
# 拎它尾巴
Hold it in the tail
# 小心它反过来咬到你
Watch out. It turns around and bites you
# 不要丢哈不是要摔到它
Don't throw and hurt it
# 不会不会它反不过来的
No worries. It can't turn around
# 这个好可爱哦
Wow it's so adorable
# 现在它要咬人了
Now it wants to bite you
# 它现在生气了
It's angry now
# 好乖哦 这个小的
So gentle. The little one
# 像我这样抓它不会咬我
Hold it like this so it can't bite me
# 它不会咬你吗
It doesn't bite you?
# 它咬不到 一只手扣住这里
It can't. Pinch it here with your hand
# 就是 掐住他的脖子
It's like, you've pinched its neck
# 掐住了它的脖子翻不过来 力气也小
Pinch its neck so it can't turn around. It's not that strong
# 大的（竹鼠）掐不住 我都不敢这样子
Bigs rats can't be pinched like this. I don't even dare
# 大的很大的力气的
Big rats are much stronger
# 大的你也怕吧
Even you feel scary of the big ones, do you?
# 怕 我也怕
I do. Even for me
# 偶尔也会被咬
I got bitten sometimes
# 今年都被咬了好几次了
I've been bitten for a few times this year
# 反正每年都被咬的
Anyway, I got bitten every year
# 我拍一下手他会不会安静下来
If I clap my hands, are they going to be quiet?
# 哇 好神奇啊
Wow. Amazing!
# 它听到声音了
They heard the sound
# 以为遇到危险了就趴着不动
They thought danger is coming. So they get down and stop moving
# 吓到它们了
They are scared
# 等一下它慢慢的就恢复过来了
And slowly they'll restart
# 现在又开始了
They've restarted now
# 一下子就安静了
Suddenly it was quiet
# 对一下子就安静了
Yeah, suddenly it's quiet
# 好神奇啊
Amazing
# 我们敲一下竹子
Let's try beating the bamboo
# 蹦的一声马上就安静了
"Bang!" and then suddenly it's all quiet
# 有竹子吗？ 有在那边
- Is there any bamboo?
- Yes, over there
# 敲一下
Let's beat it
# 有两个不听话
Two of them didn't listen
# 那边的
Over there
# 安静啦开会啦
Everyone be quiet! The meeting has started!
# 那边还有两个没安静
Still two noisy ones over there
# 我经常敲 他们都不怎么怕的
I do it too often, so they are not very scared
# 习惯了他们就不怕了
They are not scared when they get used to it
# 不习惯他们就很怕的
Otherwise they get really scared
# 这是还没断奶的
These are not weaned yet
# 它们小时候会打架吗
Do they fight when they are little?
# 不会
Nope
# 小时候不打架
They don't fight when they are little?
# 长大了都不会只要不在一起
Not even after they grow up, as long as they are not put together
# 长大了是不是争老婆才会打架
Do they fight only for a wife?
# 不是 因为只有生过崽子之后就会打架
Eh, no. They fight only after giving birth
# 哦 护崽是吧
Oh, protecting the kids
# 对 这是天性
Yeah. It's an instinct
# 真的放在一起一大推都不会打架的
They don't fight even if you put a lot of them together
# 就是这个猪在我们那边很贵
These pigs are very expensive in our place
# 很贵 是啊
- Very expensive
- Yeah
# 25元一斤
25 yuan for a jin (500g)
# 25一斤
25 yuan for a jin
# 是啊
Yeah
# 多少钱25一斤？ # 没听清
25 yuan each jin for what?
# 25一斤肉啊
This pork. 25 yuan for each jin.
# 哦
Oh
# 给它加点水
Give them some more water
# 这个猪长不大很难长大
These pigs don't grow big. They hardly grow big
# 现在应该才20多斤
They are probably only 20 jin now
# 这个猪在我们那边
If you sell them in our place, it will be...
# 要卖1000多
probably over 1000 yuan
# 这个小猪都是600到700块钱
These little pigs are six or seven hundred yuan
# 长得太慢了
They grow too slowly
# 我们就喂了一点菜叶子跟那个象草叶子给它吃
We feed them with only vegetable leaves and elephant grass leaves
# 你们家的猪好有灵性啊
Your pigs look so smart
# 对
Yeah
# 这个猪的肉是不是要香一点
Do these pigs taste better?
# 肯定香啊
Better for sure
# 天天都吃草
They are fed with grass
# 吃菜叶子
with vegetable leaves everyday
# 哦
Oh
# 那你们准备什么时候弄一只小的来吃一下
Have you thought of having a little pig to eat some time?
# 这个自己养的舍不得吃
Hmm... I raised them by myself. Don't quite want to eat
# 等长大以后在吃
I won't eat before they become big
# 有大的呀那里有一只大的
There is a big one. A big one over there
# 那个是公的
That's the male pig
# 把公猪杀了
If I kill the male pig
# 那是小猪它老爸呀 你把它老爸杀了它全体攻击我怎么办
That's the daddy of the little pigs. What if all of them attack me?
# 全家都杀了呀
You can kill them all
# 嘿嘿嘿
[laughters]
# 你好狠呀
You are so cruel
# 全家都杀了就没有恨你的了
You can kill them all, and then no one hates you
# 我们现在是去哪里弄鱼呀
Where are we going now? For the fish
# 就在上面山上
It's on the hill
# 哦是你家的是吧
Oh, is that yours?
# 对 我自己家的池塘
Yeah. That's my own pond
# 那里面有好多鱼哦
There's a lot of fish in it
# 现在差不多
Now, it's like...
# 1年多没放
One year without taking out any
# 嗯
Yeah
# 我们现在去抓鱼鱼在那边
Let's catch some fish, over there.
# 嗯
Yeah
# 那我关机了不录了
Then I'll shut down and stop recording
# 好好
Sure, sure